<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great and famous battel of Lutzen fought betweene the renowned King of Sweden, and Walstein; vvherein were left dead vpon the place between 5 and 6000. of the Swedish party, and between 10 and 12000. of the Imperialists, where the King himselfe was vnfortunatly slain ... Here is also inserted an abridgment of the Kings life, and a relation of the King of Bohemia's death. Faithfully translated out of the French coppie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12534</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103558</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839309</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839309</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3717</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02405)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3717)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1142:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great and famous battel of Lutzen fought betweene the renowned King of Sweden, and Walstein; vvherein were left dead vpon the place between 5 and 6000. of the Swedish party, and between 10 and 12000. of the Imperialists, where the King himselfe was vnfortunatly slain ... Here is also inserted an abridgment of the Kings life, and a relation of the King of Bohemia's death. Faithfully translated out of the French coppie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Variant: lacking "Faithfully .. copie" on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gustaf --  II Adolf, --  King of Sweden, 1594-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lützen, Battle of, 1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3717:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3717:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GREAT AND FAMOVS BATTEL OF LVTZEN, Fought betweene the renowned King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Walſtein;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein were left dead vpon the place between 5 and 6000. of the Swediſh party, and between 10 and 12000. of the Imperialiſts, where the King himſelfe was vnfortunatly ſlain, whoſe death counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyz'd all the other. <hi>Pappenheim, Merode, Iſolani,</hi> and divers other great Commanders were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred up like ſo many Sacrifices on the Swediſh Altar, to the memory of their King.</p>
            <p>Here is alſo Inſerted an Abridgment of the Kings life, and a Relation of the King of <hi>Bohemia's</hi> Death.</p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated out of the French Coppie.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3717:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3717:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>VVEE ſee that in the greater Maps things are expreſſed more plainly then they can be in the ſmaller, though they be draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en all by one skill: So Vertue in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is more perſpicuous, then in Plebeians; in the ſormer ſhee is drawen at length with all her dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; in the latter ſhee is limn'd in little, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, vnleſſe you approach very neere her. And, indeed, this is conſonant to Natures owne Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who ſuffers the vitali ſpirits in the body to go to the leaſt member, yea to the very fingers end; yet doth ſhee moſt plentifully beſtow them where ſhee hath the greateſt imployment for them: ſo on the vulgar ſhee conferres gifts ſutable to ſo lowe a Calling: But in Princes and Monarchs, ſhee cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuples and irradiates her ornaments, becauſe by them ſhe ſpeakes, and giues Lawes to Humanitie. Yet is not this Rule ſo generall, that it often ſuffers not an exception: for as Nature diſtinguiſheth betweene the Subject and the Prince by Soveraigntie, ſo doth ſhee betweene Prince and Prince by Vertue, and Abilitie. That this is true, this our deare Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſubject will ſerue for a liuely and cleare demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, whom neither this Age, nor any of the former could paralell in the management both of the Scepter, and the Sword. In his whole Reigne, his Prudencie at home hath not deſerued more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration then his Proweſſe abroad: For indeede, from his Youth vpwards, <hi>Mars</hi> hath beene the Spheare wherein he hath mooved, into which vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Iuſtice firſt hall'd him, and out of which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſhee appeaſed, or Death could remooue him. Hee was a Generall ere a Man, and with a yet
<pb facs="tcp:3717:3"/>vnreaped Chin mowed downe his Enemies before him. With many Kingdomes at once hee waged warre, from all which hee forced conditions ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to him and his. This was not without the amazement of all men, to ſee a Poynt oppoſe and conquer ſo vaſte a circumference. In his warres I will onely obſerue three things, His Way to Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, his behaviour in it, his Carriage after it. For the firſt, hee did animate his Souldiers rather by Fighting, then Exhorting; nor did hee challenge to himſelfe any advantage aboue the meaneſt of them, but Honour and Commaund. Hee knew that it is in Empire, as in the Bodie, where the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diſeaſes flowe from the Head: Wherefore hee work'd on their manners by his owne, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly firme Ciment of a Generall and his Armie. Hee well underſtood that Faith and Loyaltie are not to bee expected where wee impoſe thraldome and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, and therefore at times he would bee fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar as wel with the Common Souldier as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder. His Invention, and execution of all Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſtratagems were ever twinnes: for in all his Conqueſts hee owed as much to his Celeritie, as Valour. When his foes were in their Tents ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourſing of him, as a farre off, hee like the Wolfe, broke into their fable, to their irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſtoniſhment. They could not withſtand the force of his Fame, much leſſe that of his Armes. One feather more I muſt adde, without which his Victories had not been fully plumed, nor could haue ſoared ſo high, and that was this: Hee never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded any man to an Enterpriſe, in which hee would not himſelfe make one. Hee taught them as well by Hand, as Tongue. I may adde, that neither Antiquitie can, nor Poſteritie ever ſhall produce a Prince ſo patient of all Military wants, as of meate,
<pb facs="tcp:3717:3"/>drinke, warmth, ſleepe, &amp;c. all which are neceſſary to the maintenance of life. In divers ſufferings of his hee recalls to my mind the moſt accompliſht of the Romans, <hi>Cato,</hi> who leading his Troups through the contagious and poyſonous Deſerts, was ever the laſt of his Army that dranke, ſaue once, when he began to them all in water taken from a ſpring ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected to be envenomed.</p>
            <p>Thus much of his way to Victorie, now let vs come to his Deportment in it. After all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, ſuch a calme immediately enſued, that the paſſed ſtorme was ſoone forgotten, and the Enemie appeared rather like one ſuddenly wakened, then frighted. There was not any of his Victories that waſhed not her hands of all cold and innocent blood. He was ſo ſevere a Iuſticer, that he ofen reve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged the violating of his mercifull Decrees euen vpon the place, &amp; ſometime on men of qualitie, whom he affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The Lawes of Retaliation hee knew ſo well, that hee gaue to all men punctuall ſatisfaction for all offences received from his partie, according to the nature of the wrong done. For this cauſe his Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall (like the Roman) ſtood euer open. All his great Atchieuements were ever attended by Devotion within, and Circumſpection without. He firſt prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, and then provided for man, at once having an eye on his enemies next deſignes, &amp; his ſouldiers preſent neceſſities. The greateſt of his glories pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with blood &amp; ſweat, could neither change the eſtate of his mind, or copie of his countenance. The true greatneſſe of his ſpirit was ſuch, that in all his actions he placed Oſtentation behind, &amp; Conſcience before him, &amp; ſought not the reward of a good deed from Fame, but from the deed it ſelfe. I conclude this poynt with this aſſertion, That Honeſtie had as ſtrict, and great a command over him, as Neceſſitie
<pb facs="tcp:3717:4"/>over mankind. He was a Prince of ſo great &amp; cleare a fame, that Envie her ſelfe bluſhed to oppoſe it, and therefore was forced to aſſume the maske of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under which ſhe might ſecurely diſplay her inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues. Religion, Religion, it is thou that ſhouldſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, but doſt eſtrange hearts, and makeſt us ſeeke to take away euen thoſe liues that gaue us ours. Let a man haue in eminency all the Cardinall and Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall vertues, he of a contrary ſect looks on all theſe through a miſt raiſed by his malice, which makes him either not ſee them at all, or not as they are. O <hi>Ieſus, Ieſus,</hi> in thy beſt bleſſed time gather thy ſtraied flock into one fold, &amp; let Truth and Peace kiſſe each other. This teſtimony the perfections of this Prince drew from me, who was abſtemious &amp; continent in euery thing, ſaue in the ſearch of Glory and Vertue.</p>
            <p>It now remaines that I ſay ſomething of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe, in which is contained the laſt and greateſt Battell of this King, his deplored Death, and other weightie Circumſtances. The Originall is French, written by one of the ableſt Pennes of that Nation. Hee begins at the Kings comming downe into <hi>Germany,</hi> and extends his Story to his death. Of all the Moderne Hiſtories, I dare make it the <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> for it is written in a ſtile ſo Attick, and ſo judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, that it may well be called, The French <hi>Tacitus.</hi> What hath been before deliver'd in other Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes concerning this Subject, is to this nought elſe but a Faile. The full and perfect Tranſlation of this rare piece, I heere promiſe the Courteous Reader; and in the meane time, intreat him to weare as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, this Branch, by which hee may judge the whole body,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Dix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3717:4"/>
            <head>The great and famous Battell of <hi>Lutzen,</hi> fought betweene the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Walstein,</hi> vvherein were left dead vpon the place between 5. and 6000 of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> party, and betweene 10. and 12000. of the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> where the King himſelfe was vnfortunately ſlaine, whoſe death counterpoyz'd all the other. <hi>Pappenheim, Merode, Iſlonain,</hi> and divers other great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders were offered vp like ſo many ſacrifices on the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Altar, to the memory of their King.</head>
            <head type="sub">Here is alſo Inſerted an Abridgment of the Kings life, and a Relation of the <hi>King of Bohemia's Death.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE King having muſtred his Troups, and thoſe of Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Saxon-Weymar about Erffurt, the Armie received command to advance towards Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umburg.</p>
            <p>The King came thither in perſon on Saint <hi>Martins</hi> day, and cutt in pieces two Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Merode,</hi> that oppos'd him by the way. Hee was no ſooner arrived at Naum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg, but hee received Intelligence that the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3717:5"/>Enemies forces lay encamped at Leipzig, and Noerſpurg, and ſtretched thence in length as farre as Weiſſenfels, and that they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched in a place advantageous. Which proceeding of theirs obliged the King to doe the like at Naumbourg, and to ſeeke the meanes to joyne his Armie with the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, which then lay about Torgau, conſiſting of fifteene thouſand men, and reenforced with two thouſand Horſe, belonging to the Duke of <hi>Lunebourg.</hi> Hee ſent divers Poſtes to informe them of his comming, and of the courſes were to bee taken for their vniting. <hi>Walſtein,</hi> and <hi>Pappenheim</hi> being lodg'd between them, had an eye on them both, and made it their onely ſtudie to hinder their coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. On the fourteenth of November, the Scours of the King brought him word, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie had ſack'd, and abandon'd the Citie, and Caſtle of Weiſſenfells, layd plaine his Trenches, and retyred himſelfe towards Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, two German miles from Leipzig. The King hearing this newes, reſolved no longer to delay the Fight, his courage not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to temporize any further, nor to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the returne of his Poſts ſent to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour.</p>
            <p>That which confirm'd him in this his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, was the aſſurance of certaine priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners brought him by <hi>Relinguen,</hi> that <hi>Pappen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3717:5"/>was gone to Hall with ſixe Regiments Wherefore his Armie had order to march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the enemie, the fifteenth, three houres before day, and to dare him to a Battaile. The diligence of the Van was ſuch, that it reached the enemie by the ſecond houre af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Noone, and began the Aſſault. The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts failed not to make head, and a ſtrong reſiſtance. Many charges were giuen with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and loſſe equall, the victorie encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning now to this ſide, then to that, till at length the Swedes gaue fire to their ſmall Field-pieces, which pierc'd, and broke ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Imperiall Companies, and forc'd them to a Retreat. The Swedes became Maſters of the Field, and brought to the King a Standard taken from the Enemie, with this Deuiſe, <hi>La Fortune, &amp; l'Aigle Romain,</hi> Fortune, and the Roman Eagle. Hence ſome drewe this Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticke, that the enemie ſhould ere long part with the one and the other. A thicke miſte, and the night comming upon them, the Swedes were hindered in the purſuit of the enemy, and the victory.</p>
            <p>The King remained in the Field, and ſtood in order of Battaile all night, having no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhelter then his Caroach, reſolved to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low cloſe his Deſigne, and engage the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to a generall Combate. Hee communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated his Intention to the Dukes of Saxon-Weymar,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3717:6"/>and other remarkeable Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who paſſed away that night neere his Caroach, having nothing over their heads, but the Heavenly Arch, nor any thing under them, but truſſes of ſtrawe layd upon the earth. Their field furniture they left behind, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving they ſhould returne to lodge in Naum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg. But the patience of their Generall made them with eaſe paſſe over theſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences. Some of the principall Officers endeavour'd to diſwade the King from giving Battaile, alleadging that the Forces of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie were great, his Seates advantagious, their owne Armie feeble, and wearied with continuall Marches; and that it was farre ſafer to wayt for the arrivall of the Saxon, and make ſo ſtrong an vnion, as may promiſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in the equalitie of their Armies. Their reaſons were not received, but croſſed by the King, with many more ſolid, derived from the Experience of the times paſt, and the preſent aſtoniſhment of the enemie, from the courage of his Souldiers, and his advantages obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, from the Iuſtice of his Armes, from the Benediction from aboue, from the abſence of <hi>Pappenheim,</hi> and the diſcommodities he ſhould bee ſubiect to in that ſeaſon now waxing bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in caſe hee ſhould ſuffer the enemie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his Trenches, which hee had alreadie begun in many places. To which hee added
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3717:6"/>his Reputation, and how important it was to haſten the Combate, ſaying alowd, <hi>That hee could not ſuffer</hi> Walſtein <hi>to beard him, without calling him to an account, and letting him ſee by proofe he was not to be faulted, that ere this hee had not ſeene him with his ſword in his hand: that hee deſired to make tryall of his ability in the Field, and ferret him out of his burrowes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commanders perceiving by the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and tone of the King, that his decree to fight was inevitable, and their oppoſition fruitleſſe, conformed their wills by an humble obedience to his, not without reiterated pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations to ſubſcribe themſelves his, in their owne bloud, and ſeale it with the loſſe of their lives: Whereat the King rejoyced extreame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor could he containe his joy from appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his face, but by his cheerefull lookes expreſſed his inward content, and forth-with called for a new ſute of <hi>Chammois,</hi> which hee preſently put on. Then they preſented to him his Armes, and the Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Saxon Weymar, and ſundry other Princes, and Officers conjur'd him by all things deare and holy to weare his <hi>Helmet</hi> and <hi>Cuiraſſe:</hi> but they could not winne him to it, hee objecting the incumbrance, and laying his hand on the Musket bullet ſtill remaining in his ſhoulder, which to him made the leaſt weight unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3717:7"/>
            <p> The Kings deſigne was to beginne the combate by the peepe of day; but ſo thicke and darke a miſt aroſe, that it confin'd the eye to a ſmall diſtance, and rendred any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe not onely difficult, but dangerous: Wherefore the King was conſtrained to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect till the Sunne had chaſed it away, which till then had deprived him of all ſight of the Enemy. The interim (according to his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome) hee imployed in his devotions, and in making the Round of his Army, to marke the diſpoſition and countenance of his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and encourage them to <hi>fight manfully.</hi> Comming to the Quarter of the Swedes and Finlanders, he put them in Battaile Ray, and with a voice and countenance alike chee efull he thus <hi>beſpake them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Camerades is in Engliſh Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-fellowes.</note> 
               <hi>My friends, and Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades, this is the day that invites you to demonſtrate what you are; ſhew your ſelves men of valour, keepe your rankes, and fight couragiauſly for your ſelves and your King: If this day the bravery of your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſhine forth, you ſhall find the heavenly Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction perched on the poynts of your ſwords, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and a recompence of your valour; On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, if you turne backe, and baſely and fooliſhly commit the armed hand to the protection of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed foot, you ſhall find Infamy, my diſgrace, and your owne ruine, and I proteſt to you on the word of a King, that not the leaſt piece of you, or of your bones, ſhall returne againe into Swedeland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3717:7"/>
            <p> This Exhortation, delivered in a high and piercing tone, wonne from the Swedes and Finlanders onely theſe generall acclamations: <hi>That they would approve themſelves men of Honor; that they had lives only for him, which they were ambitious to preſerve in the obteining of victory, and his good graces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Swedes being placed in Rank and File, the King embattailes the Alman Regiments, and thus in few wordes exhorts them: <hi>My friends, Officers, and Souldiers, I conjure you, by your love to heaven and me, this day to maniſeſt whoſe you are; You ſhall fight not only under me, but with me, my bloud and life ſhall marke you out the way to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; Breake not your rankes, but ſecond me with courage: If you performe this, Victory is ours with all her glories, you, and your poſterity ſhall enjoy it; if you give backe, your lives and liberties have one period.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Speech was anſwered with an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall ſhout, and vowes reciprocall; <hi>That they would make it appeare they knew the way to Victory, or to death; that the King ſhould receive all ſatisfaction in their ſervice, and the Enemy ſhould acknowledge hee had to doe with men of Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walſtein,</hi> and his principall Officers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered quickely by his Scouts the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the King, and the countenance of his, and thereupon grounded this reſolution, <hi>that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3717:8"/>they muſt needs come to blowes. Walſtein</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely deſirous to avoyd the Combate; but hee was wiſely admoniſhed by ſome about him, that every ſtep his men made in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat would take from their courage, and give it to the Enemy, and bring upon his Army a Panicke feare, and an utter confuſion. Hee ſpent that whole night in digging and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching, in embattailing his Army, and planting his Artillery in diverſe places advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious, the better to ſuſtaine the ſhocke of the Enemy. <hi>Pappenheim</hi> was ſent for backe in poſt haſt, who was gone to Hall, <hi>being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deſirous to invest it,</hi> not believing that the King would give or accept of battaile, before the Forces of <hi>Saxon</hi> were arrived. In the meane time the utmoſt endeavours of <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein</hi> were not wanting to hearten his men, and layd before them Honour, Reward, their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, their Forces, the juſtice of their cauſe, which God, the Catholike Church, the Emperour, and the whole Empire juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed againſt the violence and uſurpation of a ſtranger, and all this and more he uttered in his Litter, which his Gowt would not permit him to forſake.</p>
            <p>This was ſubject to diverſe interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Some believing that indeed he felt ſome ſymptomes of that ſickeneſſe very familiar to him; others maintayned, this poſture to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3717:8"/>have no good grace on a day of Battaile, and judg'd that <hi>Walſtein</hi> was very willing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve himſelfe ſafe and ſound, that hee might hereafter ſerve his Maſter, and his party: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers averred, he was much indebted to his Gowt, which did warrant his retreat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his reproach, neceſſity commanding the ſtouteſt courage to yield to ſuch an Enemy.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, the King being ready at all poynts, and his Army embattail'd, hee would take no refection, becauſe he would be an example to his men, and loſe no time. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing placed in the head of <hi>Steinbocks</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hee thus ſpake with avoyce audible: <hi>Now, now is the time Camerades, wee muſt goe on undaunted; let us charge, let us charge in the name of God: Ieſus, Ieſus, Ieſus aide me in fighting this day, and favour my right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words were no ſooner pronounced, but he gave ſpurres to his horſe, and with his head inclined, gave a charge to a Battalion of foure and twentie Companies of Cuiraſſiers, which were eſteemd the flower of the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Army. Two Swediſh Regiments had order to ſecond him. The Artillery of the King was advanced, and five Cannon ſhot diſcharged upon the Enemy, who anſwered them with two hundred, which went off with a horrid noyſe, and lightning, but with ſmall loſſe to the Swedes, the Cannoniers of <hi>Walſtein</hi> not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3717:9"/>having well taken their aime. But the firſt ſhocke was fatall to the King, and all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: For though the Squadrons led by ſo brave a Chiefe, with an unheard of reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, gave on like Thunder on the Enemy, and made him recoyle; yet one ſhot from a Piſtoll gave him new courage, which pierced the Kings arme, and broke the bone. When thoſe next the King ſaw him bleed, they were amaz'd, and cryed out, <hi>The King is wounded.</hi> Which wordes the King heard with much diſtaſt and repining, fearing it would abate the valour of his men: wherefore diſſembling his griefe with a joyfull and undaunted looke, hee ſought to quallify the feare of his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with theſe maſculine words: <hi>The hurt is ſlight Camerades, take courage, let us make uſe of our oddes, and returne to the Charge.</hi> The Commanders that were about him, with hands lifted up, earneſtly beſought him to retire: but the apprehenſion of frighting his men, and his ambition to overcome prevailed.</p>
            <p>The Aſſault being rebegunne with vigour, and fervour, and the King fighting againe in the head of his Troopes, once more to breake thoſe Rankes that were againe made up, the loſſe of bloud, and the griefe which hee felt in the agitation of his body, enfeebled much his ſpirits and voyce, which cauſed him to whiſper theſe wordes in the eare of the Duke
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3717:9"/>of Saxon of Lavenburg; <hi>Convey me hence, for I am dangerouſly wounded.</hi> Hee had ſcarcely ended his ſpeech, and turned head to retire, when a Cuiraſſier marking this retreat, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced upon the gallop from the Battalion of the Enemy, and diſcharged his Carabin full in the ſhoulder of the King, with this inſulting ſpeech: <hi>And art thou there then? long it is that I have ſought thee.</hi> Some imagined that it was <hi>Pappenheim</hi> that gave the blow, by reaſon hee had often vaunted, that an auncient prediction was found amongſt the Records of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That a Stranger King ſhould dye by the hand of a</hi> Pappenheim, <hi>with diverſe ſcarres in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and mounted on a white Horſe.</hi> And for this cauſe (having many ſcarres in his face, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe other parts of his body ſtitcht up) hee reflected on himſelfe, and beleeved the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy ſhould bee accompliſhed by his hand. But this needes no other confutation then the abſence of <hi>Pappenheim,</hi> and the time when the King received his hurt, which was in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beginning of the Aſſault, before <hi>Pappenheim</hi> could make one of the adverſe party. I may add, that the diſcretion of this worthy Count would not have ſufferd him to runne into an errour ſo uncivill, as to ſpeake ſo undecently to a Prince of that eminency.</p>
            <p>When the King had received this mortall wound, which pierced him through and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3717:10"/>through, he fell from his Horſe, and gave up the Ghoſt, with nothing but <hi>(my God)</hi> in his mouth. He that made this accurſed ſhot was beaten downe with a ſtorme of Harquebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſados, and ſacrifiſed to the indignation of the Swedes. But while the Groome of the Kings Chamber, and diverſe others lighted to raiſe the body, the charge beganne againe more fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly then ever; the Enemy having taken notice of this blow, and concluding that all was now finiſht, and that hee ſhould have Swedes good cheape. This hindered the Kings ſervants from bearing of his body, and ſummond every man to regaine the ſtirrupe, and withſtand the foe: ſo that the King could not bee defended from receiving another pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoll ſhot in the head, and being twice runne through with a ſword: The Imperialliſts fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him even after death, and cowardly ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting his ſpeedy reſurrection. The poore Groome of his Chamber never forſooke him, but breath'd his laſt upon his Maſters carcaſſe, after the receipt of an infinity of wounds.</p>
            <p>But neither the Kings death, nor the great oddes that the enemie had, being ſtrongly entrenched in divers places, could let the Swedes (madded with their ineſtimable loſſe) from aſſaulting the Imperialliſts with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable furie, inſomuch that they compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Battalion of Cuiraſſiers (which made
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3717:10"/>the left Wing) to retire into their Trenches, whom they diſlodged about noone, and gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſeven of their Cannon, together with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Colours and Cornets.</p>
            <p>Lieutenant Coronell <hi>Relinguen</hi> received commaund to advaunce, and with three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Horſe, to charge foure Regiments of Crabbats commaunded by <hi>Iſolani,</hi> which made the right wing of the Enemy, which hee performed with ſo much braverie and courage, that hee twice pearc'd through them, and brought backe three Standards, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving behinde one of his owne. All his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers were wounded, and hee himſelfe in the ſecond onſet had his arme ſhot through with a Piſtoll bullet, which forced him to retyre. <hi>Iſolani</hi> Generall of the Crabbats loſt his life, with a great number of his men. Eighteene of his Companies charged ſome Germane Regiments that guarded the Baggage, but they were ſtoutly oppoſed, the Combate fierce, the Aſſaults reiterated, the earth dyed crimſon, and burdened with carkaſſes, the Crabbats driven backe, though not without ſome diſorder of the Germane Horſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyled amongſt the Carts: but this diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage the Enemy could not eſpie, by reaſon of a thicke cloud which then aroſe, and gaue the Germanes opportunitie to ranke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:3717:11"/>
            <p> The Imperiall Commaunders, <hi>Galas, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode,</hi> and <hi>Holok,</hi> longing to recover their Seat, and Cannon lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, tooke ſelected Bands, fired the foure Corners of Lurzen, to blinde the Swedes, and keepe them from piercing that ſide, to the ſuccour of their friends. This Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay was followed by ſucceſſe, the Trench force by the Imperialliſts, the ſeven pieces of Cannon loſt, regained, and ſome Swediſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments diſordered.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Saxon Weymar ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the confeſion of his men, and beeing ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiz'd by <hi>Kinphauſen</hi> of the Kings death, was extreamely incenſed, and proteſting hee had not ſo baſe a wiſh as to ſurviue him, hee ranne (with his head couched) on the enemy, ſeconded by the Regiments of the Prince of <hi>Auhalt,</hi> and Count <hi>Lowenſlein.</hi> Then the fight became obſtinate on both ſides, the Charges redoubled, the Carkaſes piled up, the Pikes broken, and the difference come to bee deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by dint of Sword. The eye of man, nor that greater of the World ever beheld a Iouſt more furious. The Imperialiſtes ſtroue to hold their advantage recover'd, and the Swedes to diſpoſſeſſe them of it. The Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> did wonders that day. Thrice like Lightning ſhot hee through the Forces of the Enemie, nor could a wound received on the left Arme cauſe him to leaue the field, before
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3717:11"/>hee had conſtrained the Enemie to abandon the Cannon, and his Poſt.</p>
            <p>The winning of this opened him the way to the conqueſt of another: For this valiant Prince preſſed the Imperialiſt ſo hard, that hee againe diſrank'd them, and compelled them to quit another Poſt, guarded with thirteene Cannon. His dexteritie in the drilling of his men, in the opening and ſhutting of his rankes was ſuch, that they received little or no hurt from the Enemies Cannon. The Duke un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted, pierc'd through the clouds of ſmoke, diſplac'd the enemie, and made himſelfe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter likewiſe of this place, and of the Cannon, and droue the enemie to a confuſed Retreat. The ſlaughter was great, and the Swedes well blouded, made good life of their advantage, and the diſorder of their foes, paſſing over their bellies, killing all that came in their way, and ſtopping their eares againſt all motiues for quarter.</p>
            <p>The Duke poſſeſſed of this place, and Maſter of the Field, betweene two and three in the afternoone, thinking there was but one Poſt to force, ſeared by a Windmill, and guarded by three Imperiall Regiments, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to remooue them, ſending in the meane time ſundry Squadrons to chaſe the fugitiues. But then the fight grew more cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell then ever: For <hi>Pappenheim</hi> was returned
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3717:12"/>from Hall, and came upon the gallop with certaine freſh Regiments. His Reputation, and his concouragement gaue new ſpirits to the Runawayes, and call'd them to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. The Duke having notice of this, quits this place, new ranks and encourages his men, and giues <hi>Pappenheim</hi> a meeting in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. All the Charges paſt were nothing in reſpect of theſe latter. <hi>Pappenheim</hi> imployed his utmoſt cunning and diligence, and ſhewed himſelfe in all places in the Head of his Troupes, to embolden them. On the other ſide, the Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> fixt a reſolution either to die, or overcome; and the Swedes and Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers enrag'd for the death of their King, fought like Lions, and deſperately ranne upon the enemy. The Artillery advanced, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to thunder, and to enter divers Battalions, and to make legges and Armes to flie from one place to another. The ſmaller ſhot was alſo ſe violent, that the Squadrons encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the palpable darkneſſe cauſed by the ſmoake without knowledge of their parties. This furious ſhocke continned two houres, with equall loſſe to both, Victorie opening her armes to imbrace now one ſide, then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Galas, Merode,</hi> and <hi>Holok</hi> were wounded to death, and a Cannon ſhot cut off <hi>Pappenheim</hi> by the middle.</p>
            <p>His death, and the loſſe of divers other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3717:12"/>Commanders, ſtagger'd the Imperialiſtes, as much as that of the kings incenſed the Swedes. Then the enemy (upon the receite of a newe ſalute from foure and twenty Cannon, which pierc'd their thickeſt Troupes) began to flie, and the Swedes preſſed and purſude them far within night, which favour'd the retreat of the fugitiues, and hinder'd the Swedes from ranging further in the chaſe. Indeede they were ſo tyred, that they had neither breath, nor force furtherto follow them. The Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialliſts (giving fire to their campe, and part of their baggage,) tooke ſome the way of Leipzig, others that of Leutmeritz, towards the Frontiers of Bohemia, whither it was thought <hi>Walstein</hi> was gone, (having heard of the loſſe of the Battell) to find a ſafe place of retreat, and to gather together his diſperſed Troupes.</p>
            <p>The Swedes remained in poſſeſſion of the Enemies campe, and moſt of his Baggage, of one and twentie exquifite Cannon, beſides in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriour ones, and a multitude of Standards and Corners. Vpon the muſtering of their Armie, they found wanting, (over and aboue the incomparable, and irreparable loſſe of their King) the Major Generall <hi>Iſslet,</hi> and other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronells, and Officers. A Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> a Count of <hi>Nilis,</hi> the Coronels <hi>Brandeſtein, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſtein, Relinguen,</hi> and <hi>Winchell</hi> received that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3717:13"/>day deepe and honourable wounds. The Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar alſo was hurt, to whoſe valour and conduct the Swedian partie (after God) owes the glorie of that day, more bloudy by far, then that which was ſought the yeare paſt in the neighbouring fields of Leip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zig. The Duke <hi>Erneſt</hi> of Weymar alſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated himſelfe into the hearts of all men by his courage, and leading that day. The Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of theſe two Princes, and thoſe of the Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> of the Count of <hi>Leweſtein,</hi> of Coronell <hi>Brandeſtein,</hi> and the two Swediſh Coronells, ſurnamed, <hi>The Blew, and the Yellow,</hi> bore the brunt of that day. The Swedes loſt betweene fiue and ſixe thouſand men, and the enemie betweene ten and twelue thouſand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining on the place, and two thirds of their Armie ruin'd, and diſperſed, beſides the death or mortall wounds of divers of their remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Commaunders, as <hi>Calas, Merode, Holok, Piccolomini' Iſolani,</hi> and divers others. <hi>Pappen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim</hi> aboue all the reſt was bewayled by his partie, and not without juſt cauſe; his courage, his Conduct, his Vigilancie, and Experience having conſpired to ranke him in the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers eſteeme amongſt the braveſt Generalls of theſe times.</p>
            <p>But this glorious Victory of the Swedian Armie ſuffered an Ecclipſe by the death of that truely great King, who was the ſoule of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3717:13"/>his Friends, and the terrour and ſcourge of his Enemies. His bodie could not bee found till the next day, when after a curious ſearch it was diſcover'd amidſt the dead heapes rifled, and halfe naked, and ſo disfigur'd with bloud, and durt, that hee could hardly bee knowne. This at once ſo dolefull and glorious a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the end of ſo great a Monarch, work'd ſo ſtrongly, and effectually on the hearts of his Souldiers, that with teares and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for a loſſe ſo irreparable, they made an unanimous Vow, upon the place to revenge his death, and make him reviue in the rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous purſuite of his Deſignes, which hee had ſo often conjur'd them to continue, eſpecially a little before this Battell, when hee ſeem'd to preſage his ende, touching which hee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed often and ſeriouſly with many of his familiars. Amongſt other paſſages, the King marking the multitude of people that flock'd about him at his entry into Naumbourg, three dayes before the Battell, and hearing their ſhouts of Ioy, and this generall acclamation, <hi>Long liue the King,</hi> as if now they had nothing to feare, ſince hee was preſent, hee made to the ſtanders by this ſhort but memorable ſpeech: <hi>Our Affaires anſwere our deſires, but I doubt God will puniſh mee for the folly of the people who attribute too much to mee, and eſteeme mee as it were their God, and therefore hee will make them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3717:14"/>ſhortly ſee I am but a man. Hee bee my witneſſe it is a thing diſtaſtfull to mee. What ever befall mee, I ſhall receiue it as proceeding from his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine will: In this onely I reſt fully ſatisfied, that hee will not leaue this great Enterpriſe of mine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeventeenth of November immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately following the day of Battaile, and the Kings death Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar retir'd to Weiſſenfels to take a generall review of his Army, and to give reſt, and breath to his over wearyed Troopes. By the review of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, it appeared that his Army was be tweene fifteene and ſixteene thouſand ſtrong. The Duke imparted his preſent eſtate, and all other neceſſary particulars to the Court of Saxon, and urg'd the Electour to an uniting of their Forces, to the end they might follow cloſe their deſigne, and purſue <hi>Walſtein</hi> to the remoteſt parts of Auſtria. After this, all the Army, as well Swediſh as Germane, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed in the election of Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> for their Generall, and tooke a new Oath faithfully to ſerve him, who had deſerved ſo well of the Swedian party by ſo many benefits, by his vigilancy, his conduct, and the greatneſſe of his ſame in Warre: but above all, by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and incomparable valour, of which he made ſo oportune and cleare a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on that bloudy day of Battaile. The
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3717:14"/>Chancellour <hi>Oxeſterne</hi> (who lay when about Frankfort) was ſent for in all haſt to manage the affaires of the Chancery Royall removed to Erfurt; but chiefely, to ſerve and counſell the deſolate and diſconſolate Queen, environ'd wih griefes and croſſes inexprimable, yet but equall to the greatneſſe of her loſſe. The ſaid Chancellour, and the Chevalier Rache ſerved happily to rectify ſundry diſorders, and to raiſe the ſpirits of ſuch as were dejected; but principally, to ſtop the floud of teares flowing from the eyes of this moſt vertuous Princeſſe, and to replant in her mind generous and maſculine reſolutions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>De la Gorde</hi> was ſent for in poſt haſt, who was imbarked in Swedeland with certaine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of Swedes, and Finlanders, to bring a ſupply to the Campe Royall, and reinforce it, the dead King beeing anchor'd in this maxime, to make continuall levies, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the number of his Armies) that ſo hee might have men at will to fill up thoſe empty Companies, which the Sword, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallity, and many other militarie miſeries might unhappily depopulate.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding the death of this mighty Prince, the aſtoniſhment and fright of the Enemy was ſuch, that hee baſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke diverſe ſtrong and impregnable places in the Electorate of Saxony. Amongſt others
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3717:15"/>the City of Leipzig was forſaken, and the Caſtle raſed to the ground, Chemnits was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, Zwickaw inveſted and forced, the Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> following cloſe his good fortune, and making good uſe of the Enemies amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. To this hee was animated the more, by the fixt decree of the conſederate Princes, to make all faſt, and more and more to knit a firme Vnion with the Swedes, that ſo joyntly, that ſo both of them joyntly might execute, and fulfill the intentions and exhortations of the deceaſed King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walſtein</hi> having notice betimes of his mens infortunity, and the advantage of the Swedes, recovered Leipſig that night, and before day tooke the way of Leutmeritz, where hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected is disbanded men, and added to them ſixe freſh Regiments that had not beene engaged in the Battaile. After the often ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his Poſts to all parts, at length <hi>Altrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> had order from the Duke of Bavaria to joyne halfe his Army to that of <hi>Walſtein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the ſomiſerable defeat of the Imperialiſts, bonefires were made in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe parts of Bavaria, for the death of the King, and <hi>Te Deum</hi> chanted aloude through all the ſtreets of Ingolſtatt, and Ratisbone. But theſe vaine fires, and triumphs ſeru'd for ſo many Trumpets, to ſound forth the praiſe and glory of the departed King, ſince in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3717:15"/>Enemies owne judgement his death was thought ſufficient to counterpoize the diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſlaughter of ſo puiſſant an Army: And indeed, except this accurſed blow, there was no one circumſtance, that did not oblige the Imperiall partie to a funerall Equipage. Nothing was more to bee admired then the moderation of the Court of Vienna, which expreſſed no joy in triumph, or exultation. They contented themſelves with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of a few Ordnance, to make the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people believe they had the better of the day. Some judg'd this modeſt behaviour to proceed from ſenſible loſſes, ſuffered in the Battaile, from the conſideration of the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Forces, and the difficulty to ſet on foot againe an Army of that vaſtneſſe. Others deemed it to proceed from the diſperſed ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the Emperours death, which they thought countervail'd that of the King, and caſt the Imperiall Court into an irrecoverable dejection</p>
            <p>The failing of the Saxon to appeare in the Field on the day of Battaile, (when his aide concerned his owne honour and the Kings good) was attributed to the like ſad accident, a rumour being divulged, not onely of the Dukes death, but the manner of it, to wit, ſuddaine Apoplexie: But theſe falſe bruits, both of the one and the other, were contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3717:16"/>by aſſuted newes that both the Princes were living.</p>
            <p>That the Saxon was not dead, hee gave good proofs, reſolving to take occaſion by the lock to revenge the ruine of his Cities, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>population of his Countrey, and to hinder the Imperialifts from ſending into his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions any more Incendiaries.</p>
            <p>The continuance of the Emperours life was favourable to his party; the very name and ſplendour of Majeſty being of vertue to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, and retaine diverſe ſpirits in devotion, and obedience to the Auſtrian Line, which elſe perhaps might have followed the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of the victorious Triumpher.</p>
            <p>But will'ſt the fooliſh people ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, or by deſigne, or credulity, the death of theſe two Princes, there came too aſſured newes from Nayence of the King of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia's death. When this vnfortunate Prince was ready to take a new poſſeſſion of his Countrey, and the conditions drawne up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene him, the King of Sweden, and the Governour of Frankendale, hee was ſurpriſed in Nayence with a contagious diſeaſe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after his returne from Deux-ponts, where hee had viſited a Prince of his alliance. The care and ſufficiency of the Phiſitian was ſo great, that he quickly expelled the peſtilent quality, and ſet him in all appearnace free from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3717:16"/>danger; but the great calamities through which hee had paſſed, had much eſtranged his Conſtitution from its firſt puritie, and quite altred his colour, and complexion. When he thought to quit his tedious bed, and take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Frankendale, it unfortunately hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> death came to his eare, which wrought ſo on his mind, and body, that his diſeaſe was aggravated, and his death enſued on the 29. of November. His death was much deplored by thoſe of his bloud, by his ſervants and ſubjects, yet did their griefe receiue an allay by his devotion, and his laſt words full of faith and pietie.</p>
            <p>The life of this Prince was a meere Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, and like a Picture with many faces. His entry into the Electorate was glorious, his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning happy, his Vertues eminent, and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hee was by the whole Empire. His Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and friends within and without Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the conſideration of his Houſe, of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and the great Bodie that depended on his direction, were the cauſe of his electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Crowne of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> which was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to him, and all <hi>Germanie,</hi> which felt the ſad accidents that attended this Comet, and was foorthwith invaded by an univerſall Warre in her heart, and all her quarters, which hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince forſooke her, having engaged all the Imperiall States and Provinces, every one
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3717:17"/>whereof to this day carries her markes. And though this Prince hath ſought all meanes of reconciliation, hoping that way to quench this Wild-fire; yet hath hee from time to time found ſuch fatall oppoſitions, and ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſted malice in the incenſed partie, that all the motiues, propoſitions, and interceſſions of great Kings haue hetherto beene unprofitable; and this good Prince hath beene conſtrained to liue an exile from his Countrey. At length when a moſt pleaſing proſpect laid at once open to his view the frontiers of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and the end of his afflictions, a ſuddaine death deprived him of his ſight, and the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo delightfull an object.</p>
            <p>The calamitie of this Prince hath given occaſion to many licentious tongues, and pens to declaime againſt him, and unjuſtly to judge of his cauſe by the ſad event. Thoſe that were of his more inward acquaintance, avow that hee was unfortunate beyond defect, and that the moſt magnanimous, and Heroicke ſoule could beare afflictions with no greater moderation and patience, then he did. If ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his vertues haue beene clouded and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured by his infelicity, yet are there more which his darker fortune could not hinder from ſhining forth, and ſtriking envie blind. His great Family, his Extraction, his Allies and Confederates, and his Princely vertues,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3717:17"/>me thinkes ſhould haue contained within the bounds of Honour, and truth, certaine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary, Satyricke Spirits, who haue common places of prayſes, and Invectiues, which they draw forth to exalt, or depreſſe whom they pleaſe, and mainetaine their looſer vaine at the coſt of Princes, and play upon their perſons, qualities, and eſtates, whom the greatneſſe of their births ſhould priviledge from ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelies. Wee owe honour, and reſpect to Princes of what party ſoever; whether they bee Friends, Enemies, or Neuters: And I thought this ſhort Apologie due to my ſo much deplored Subject, whom his miſeries rendered to ſome contemptible, though by others he was truely honoured in the midſt of his diſgraces, and afflictions. The King of Sweden gaue many braue teſtimonies of him, being forced oftentimes to giue him a ſtop in the carreere of honour, leſt courage ſhould engage him too ſarre, exhorting him to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his life, the good of his Countrey, and the publike cauſe.</p>
            <p>All the comfort of his Subjects is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that generous unparalell'd Princeſſe, and in her faire line, and numerous iſſue which promiſeth them one day an entire liberty, and the reeſtabliſhment, and ſubſiſtence of a houſe ſo many wayes conſiderable, as being one of the firſt, and moſt ancient of Europe.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3717:18"/>
            <p> The Reader, I doubt not, will pardon this digreſſion of the Souldier, who held himſelfe obliged to ſpeake for a Prince, who had beene a long time the common But of all afflictions, and infultations. That which hath made him the more bold, and earneſt in his defence, is the neare alliance of this Prince to mighty Monarchs. I ſhut up all concerning this point in this Aſſertion, that all Princes haue a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt in the honour of their equals, and ſhould all joyne to place their Crownes, and purple aboue the reach of Envie.</p>
            <p>The death of theſe two Kings was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to make the Germans approue of the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, and prognoſticks of their great Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger <hi>Herlicius,</hi> who had noted this Moneth of <hi>November,</hi> as fatall to great Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, and foretold by the Aſpects, and fiery conſtellations, the tragicall encounters of theſe two great Armies, and the death of ſuch eminent perſons, as may well compoſe the greateſt part of the Hiſtory of our time.</p>
            <p>The Swedes were even wedded to ſorrow for the death of their King, vowing they would more willingly haue ſuffered the loſſe of many battailes then that of him, if it had lyen in their power to diſpoſe of the Arreſts of Heaven, and the ſatall lawes of the eternall Providence, which with a Diamantine poynt markes all things, and giues them a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3717:18"/>which never can bee changed, or defaced.</p>
            <p>Indeed all the dayes of this Moneth of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> were at ſtrife for Superioritie in evill, but the ſixteenth overcame, to which all ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhall giue a brand, in that it gaue ſo ſtrange an alteration to the face of Chriſtendome. The battaile ſought on that day is enobled by many memorable accidents, which exalts it aboue thoſe of former Ages. Amongſt others are remarkeable the ſmall number of the victors, and the multitude of the vanquiſt, the violent and ſurious charges, the durance of the fight, the doubtfull event of the combat, when victory (as if the had beene the daughter of <hi>Ianus</hi>) had two faces, and looked two waies; the piles of the dead, the loſſe of eminent Commanders, and the different effect which one and the ſame cauſe wrought in both parties, the Kings death kindling indignation and deſire of revenge in the boſome of the Swede, and the death of <hi>Pappenheins,</hi> and other great Commanders, begetting an aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in the hearts, and lookes of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts. And wee may well affirme, that amongſt all the Accidents of that ſaddeſt of daies, this particular hath bin moſt remarkable; that the Swedes having loſt their King in the firſt ſhocke, this unparaleld miſchance, ſerved rather to confirme, then ſhake their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3717:19"/>courage, and was one of the moſt apparant cauſes of the victory.</p>
            <p>This alſo raiſed as high as Heaven the Kings renowne, that in his fall hee cruſht in pieces ſo vaſt a body, and the hearts of his men were ſo inflamed with this his diſaſter, that after his death they made the palme and the Lawrell to ſpring out of his blood. Nor was the life of this Prince leſſe famous then his death.</p>
            <p>His youth was exerciſed in great affaires, which hardened his body to endure travell, and armed his mind againſt all finiſter acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and infus'd into him a courage which might eaſily bee provoked, never ſubdued. The entrie of his Raigne (which was the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of this age, and the Seventeenth of his) was thorny, and ſallebrous. At one, and the ſame time hee was confronted by the Danes, the Polonians, and the Muſcovites, who on all ſides aſſaulted him: And though their motives to warre were diverſe, yet all their intentions, like ſo many lines met in this Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to ruine the Swede. Sometimes hee ſhewed himſelfe on the Frontiers of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, ſometimes on thoſe of Muſcovia, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times againe on thoſe of Livonia, and all with that promptneſſe and celerity, that his Enemies believed his body to bee ubiquitary. And his troubles were increaſed by corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3717:19"/>of many of his Subjects to a baſe revolt. But his valour, his dexterity, and the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all travaile of his body and mind were ſuch, that hee paſſed through theſe, and greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments without ſtop, or diminution of his Fame. His compoſition with the Danes, and Muſcovites was honourable, and to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. The quarrell betweene him and the Polonian was not about any ſmall petty Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorie; but the Crowne and Scepter it ſelfe, and therefore hardly to be decided.</p>
            <p>The Proweſſe and agility of this King were ſuch, that the Polonians ſaw him in all parts, like another <hi>Hanniball,</hi> before their gates; and after many great loſſes received in Livonia, and Pruſſia, they tooke counſell of the Pillow, and (to preſerve the remainder of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries unviolated) concluded to come to a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, on which attended a Truce, which from their ſoules they wiſh'd had beene a Peace, whereby their repoſe might bee eternized. Our youthfull <hi>Mars</hi> had not a ſoule ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, as to bee contented to weare onely the Lawrell of the North. More wreathes were prepared for him, and a Theater more ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and glorious. Poſterity will hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that what this Prince hath done was by a man feſible. That the conqueſt of ſo many vaſt Provinces, and the ruine of ſo many Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies was the worke onely of two yeares, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3717:20"/>a few moneths. That a puiſſant Empire, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable in her greatneſſe, in her ſupports, in her extenſion, in her Armies, in her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and ſucceſſe, fortifyed with ſo many Garriſons, who hath for her bounds the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, and the Alps, ſhould in ſo ſhort a time be forc'd to put on the yoak. A man would think infinite Forces were required to manage well an Enterpriſe of this nature, and greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>The perſonall qualities of this Prince were admirable. His externall bravery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in a ſweet yet majeſticall aſpect, in a comely ſtature, in a piercing eye, in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding voyce, in an agility, and univerſall application to all ſuch as might hinder or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him. But the great gueſts that lodg'd within were farre more illuſtrious, a quicke ſpirit, a ſollid judgement, an incomparable wiſedome, an inexprimable courage, an inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable nature, and an admirable conduct, which were the happy inſtruments of all his victories, and the embelliſhment of this rare piece. I may juſtly adde his Encampments, his Diſcipline, his foreſight, his direction, and unequall'd Induſtrie. Nor was his readineſſe leſſe in the diſpoſition of his affaires, in the governement of his men, and his complying with their ſeverall humours, which made him as well Lord of hearts, as Provinces and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But above all the reſt, his devotion was
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3717:20"/>conſpicuous, and his frequent pious exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which received no interruption by his moſt ſerious imployments. And (which draweth neere to a miracle) hee himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and executed all things. It ſuffiſed not him to bee onely a Generall, but hee would alſo bee a Captaine, and Engenier, a Serjeant, a Cannonier, a common Souldier, or of any Militarie calling. The moſt dangerous oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences dazled not his judgement, but then was he moſt venturous when his valour was moſt required. Hee never formed a milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry project, in the execution whereof hee would not himſelfe make one. And (which bred in all an amazement) hee was never wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, though ever buſied, as if action had been his nouriſhment. I will cloſe up the Panne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyricke of this Worthy with this affirmation, that in him all imaginable brave parts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to make him the greateſt, and moſt able Captaine of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>There was nothing in him the leaſt way blameable but his choller, to which the leaſt provocation gave fire: an humour familiar to fiery ſpirits chafed with continuall buſineſſe, which often falls out croſſe. But hee had a corrective ever ready, which was an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing courteſy, and ſweetneſſe to him natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, which ſtopp'd and repair'd the breach his Anger had made. For any haſty ſpeech
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3717:21"/>he would give ſatisfaction, not onely to men of eminency, who might juſtly be offended, but to thoſe alſo of the meaneſt condition, borne to ſuffer. In acknowledgement of his nature ſo apt to take fire at the leaſt diſtaſt, he would often ſay; <hi>That hee was willing often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to beare with others infirmities, as the flegme of ſome, and the wine of others, and that therefore reciprocally his choller deſerved ſome ſupport.</hi> And, to ſay truth; this paſſion may challenge, and winne connivence from him who ſhall duely conſider his working ſpirit, never weakned, though ever bended; as alſo his extraordinary vertues, and his gentleneſſe, which, upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, made him familiar with the meaneſt of his ſouldiers, ſo farre was hee from being pufft up with proſperity, or rayſing his mind with his fortune.</p>
            <p>Some note another overſight in this Prince, that he did not better diſtinguiſh betweene the dueties of a Carabin, and a Generall, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelfe to all dangers, and was too prodigall of a bloud ſo precious. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the truth, it is not ſo much to bee won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, that he loſt his life in this famous Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail, as that he parted not with it long before in ſo many Encounters, where his life ranne the ſame hazard with the baſeſt of his ſouldiers. And in his defence this may worthily bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, that the valour of his men depended
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3717:21"/>on his example, and all his victories had for their originall his preſence, and forwardneſſe in all Battailes, which like a heavenly aſpect ſent downe influences, and irradiations into the ſpirits of his ſouldiers, and terrour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement into thoſe of his Enemies.</p>
            <p>The Souldier hath attempted to draw this Prince to the life, and aſſures himſelf, that they who have had the honour to ſee, and ſerve him in his wars, wil confeſſe that the portraict hath ſome aire of his face, if not drawne to the life. And hee beleeves withall, that they who have felt the puiſſance of his Armes will be the firſt to extoll and magnify his worth, that thereby they may leſſen their owne loſſes, juſtify their diſgraces, and ſhew to the world that ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull an Organ was required to operate on them with ſuch ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>Amongſt other circumſtances, this is the moſt agreeable, and worthy of obſervation, that this Prince hath left his affaires in an eſtate ſo proſperous, and advantagious. The Swedian party is poſſeſſed of two thirds of Germany, of the beſt Cities, of moſt of the Rivers from the Viſtule to the Danube, and Rheine. It hath alſo ten Armies diſperſed through the higher and lower Saxonies, Sile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Moravia, Bavaria, Franconia, Suabe, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia, and the Circle of the Rhein. This par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is alſo back'd, and countenanc'd within by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3717:22"/>the principall Forces of the Empire, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out by great Kings and States, who thinke themſelves intereſted in the ſupport of it, and preferre ſure friends before doubtfull and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, who will eternally remember the leaſt loſſe, or affront received, and, opportunity ſerving, bee ready to revenge it. To this may be adjoyned the experience of the times paſt, which demonſtrates unto us how well in the Mantuan warre they requited the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits received from that houſe at a dead lift, which ſerves for an infallible argument of their dealings.</p>
            <p>It now remaines that the Princes, and States united continue to make good the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages bequeath'd them, by baniſhing all jealouſies, ſuppreſſing of factions, extirpating of Schiſmes, and partiallities, deciding of all diſputes ariſing from their Genealogies, by conferring offices on men, not of great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, but ability, by making uſe of the times preſent and paſt, by quickly ſeconding their conſultation with action, and by a ſtraight conjunction of their Councells, and Forces to ſeeke their owne preſervation in that of the Empire. In any of which being wanting, neither the care and paines of the deceaſed King, nor their owne Armies, or advantages can ſecure them from being a miſerable prey to their Enemies, and wretched ſpectacle to their friends.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3717:22"/>
            <p> The truth is, hitherto the Princes and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls united have much abated the pride of the Enemy, by deceiving his hopes, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, and making it evident by their proceedings that they were not in vain ſo long train'd up in the Kings ſchoole, but were ſtill mindfull of his inſtructions and diſcipline, and that his death did but concenterre, and redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their vigour. The Dukes of Weymar tread on <hi>Walſteins</hi> heeles, whom ſome report to bee wounded, others dead in the Forreſt which lyes betweene Fraveſtein and Kloſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grappe. If he be deceaſed, he ſerves as another ſacrifice due to the Kings tombe. <hi>Tubal</hi> keeps the greateſt part of Sileſia, and Moravia in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. The Prince of Birkenfield ſhuts up all paſſages to the Bavarians, within the circle of Ingolſtat and Ratisbone. <hi>Horne</hi> is Maſter of Alſatia, and hath joyned to it the Conqueſt of Schletſtatt. <hi>Colman</hi> and <hi>Kent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zingen</hi> have Senfeld, nothing remaining in thoſe parts unconquer'd, but <hi>Frebourg</hi> which they batter, and Briſſack which they play with. <hi>Baudiſin</hi> marcheth through the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhopricke of Cullen without reſiſtance, and traverſeth his Galleries (maugre the Count of <hi>Gransfield</hi>) from the river of Weſper even to the gates of Cullen. The Troopes of <hi>Wir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg</hi> advance towards the Lake of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and are reſolved to make good proofe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3717:23"/>of their courage. To be briefe, the Swedes ſhew that they have no great deſire to repaſſe the Sea, no more then have the Germans to refall into their wonted ſlavery.</p>
            <p>But though the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> hath left his partie in an Eſtate proſperous, yet wee muſt needs confeſſe, that the enemie deriues from his death great Advantages, and that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe of a little Lead hath profited him as much as the gaining of many millions, in that the ſeverall Heads of the Swediſh Armies are ſubject and prone to jealouſies and miſconcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which giues him meanes and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to preſerue what hee yet holds, to calme ſeditions, to recall long-baniſht peace, and once more to replant her in the Empire.</p>
            <p>If hee make good uſe of his loſſes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunities, wee ſhall ſee him foorthwith to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon all counſells tending to blood, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to haue a care, left by the oppreſſion of Princes he make them deſperate, to recall his ſtrayed Subjects by a generall Pardon of all their offences, and ſeeke to raigne by Loue, not Feare. Hee will then no more violate Peace, and the publique Faith, under the pretext of Conſcience, which ought to be perſwaded, not forced, as depending on another Tribunall then that of men. This way to reſt and quiet, he is invited alſo to take and perſiſt in, becauſe he may now peaceably enjoy all his due rights
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3717:23"/>and Titles, the death of the King having cur'd him of the deadly Feare hee was in, leſt this magnanimous Prince ſhould yet fore higher, and aſpire to new Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dems, and make good his Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram, by changing the name of <hi>Guſtavus</hi> into <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
